Okay, בוקר טוב boker tov everybody. Today's דף daf is ט"ז. tet
zayin. We pick up with the... I'm sorry, not ט"ז, tet zayin,
י"ז. yud zayin. Whoops, sorry about that. Today's דף daf is י"ז.
yud zayin. We will, God willing, end the פרק perek and begin
the second one today. We pick up with the משנה mishna in
the middle of ט"ז עמוד ב'. tet zayin amud bet. After the
previous משנה mishna had listed the תם, tam, what types of things
that are identified as תם tam as, you know, unlikely occurrences or
whatever, unhabituated, and מועד muad things that are regular occurrences, this משנה
mishna deals with the הלכה halakha implications about it. מה בין תם
למועד? ma bein tam lemuad? What's the difference between תם tam and
מועד? muad? אלא שהתם משלם חצי נזק מגופו. ella shehatam mishalem chatzi
nezek migupo. תם tam pays half damages and it comes out of
the body of the animal itself, and we will see about that
later, the whole debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon whether you actually automatically become a part owner in the
body of the animal or what exactly that means, but it certainly
the cost does not exceed the cost of the goring damaging animal.
ומועד משלם נזק שלם מן העליה. umuad mishalem nezek shalem minaliya. And
מועד muad pays full damages from עליה, aliya, from the best. And
we'll see what עליה aliya means in the first line in the
גמרא. Gemara. You already have a question.
I feel like we should have had this משנה mishna earlier.
Oh, give us a break. I will tell you that compared to
other מסכתות, masechtot, this מסכת masechet is extremely well laid out and
organized. I mean, it starts with, you know, here are the concrete
cases in the תורה, Torah, let's abstract it to the general principle,
let's talk about what some of those general principles are although it
did it in very cryptic language. You know, let's identify what are
the תמים tamim and what are the מועדים, muadim, and let's tell
you what the difference is between the הלכות halachos between תמים tamim
and מועדים. muadim. You know, I mean, it's true the גמרא's Gemara's
been dealing with this all along, but if you think about the
משניות, mishnayot, they are extremely well laid out. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. מאי עליה? mai aliya? What does עליה aliya
mean?
אמר רבי אלעזר במעולה שבנכסיו, amar Rabbi Elazar bimeula shebinichasav, the best
of the property, which means, you know, well, we'll see what best
means. You might think it means like מיטב, meitav, but really all
it's really going to mean is that it doesn't come from the
body of the animal.
וכן אומר, vechen omer, comes from any property that the person has.
וישכב חזקיהו עם אבותיו ויקברוהו, vayishkav Chizkiyahu im avosav vayikberuhu, that Michael
see, check, okay, anyway, the...
וישכב חזקיהו עם אבותיו ויקברוהו במעלה קברי בני דויד. vayishkav Chizkiyahu im
avosav vayikberuhu bemaaleh kivrei bnei David. חזקיהו Chizkiyahu lay down with his
fathers and they buried him in the מעלה maaleh of the, of
the graves of the sons of דוד. David. What does מעלה maaleh
mean? ואמר רבי אלעזר במעלה אצל מעולים שבמשפחה. veamar Rabbi Elazar bemaaleh
etzel meulim shebamishpacha. He was buried by the most, you know, prestigious
ones of the family. ומן ניהו דוד ושלמה, uman nichu David uShlomo,
so he was buried right near דוד ושלמה, David uShlomo, one of
the great kings of the Davidic line. Okay, so anyway, it's interesting
though that it says במעלה bemaaleh because מעולה meula really just means,
it doesn't mean like, you know, again as we know, when you,
I mean, okay, if you get land, you get the מיטב, meitav,
but if you get מטלטלין, metaltelin, it's anything, but the point is
that it's, it's not limited to just the body of the animal.
Now because we mentioned this פסוק pasuk by חזקיהו, Chizkiyahu, we're going
to have some nice אגדתא agadata leading us through, bringing us through
to the end of the פרק. perek. Let's take a look.
One second, Rabbi, let me just... so this is saying that נזק
nezek min ha... מטלטלין, metaltelin, no problem, in other words it's...
yes, of the, of the owner himself whose animal did the נזק.
nezek. There's no liens if he dies and it goes on to
the heirs or he sells his property, you can only collect from
the land, but from the person himself, you take מטלטלין metaltelin or
קרקע. karka. I understand.
Who makes that choice?
Well, that's an interesting question, right? The גמרא Gemara earlier... I mean,
if he's willingly paying, then he makes the choice. If בית דין
beis din have to seize it, so that was the discussion the
גמרא Gemara had before. Maybe when בית דין beis din has to
seize it, בית דין beis din seizes the מטלטלין metaltelin and not
the... it's not exactly, you know, בית דין beis din sort of
decides, I think, what to seize, and there's a whole set of
משניות mishnayot in ערכין Erchin around some of those discussions, but yeah,
it might depend whether who, whether he's willingly paying or not. But
if he's willingly paying, he can choose what to pay.
Yeah, I mean, you know, the גמרא Gemara sort of reinterpreted it,
but as פשט pshat to me, מעולה מן הנכסים meula min hanechasim
doesn't necessarily mean... you know what I mean.
I understand. The idea of אפילו סובין, afilu suvin, which has been
a running theme in the גמרא, Gemara, has not been in the
משנה. mishna. And you know, it's one ברייתא brayta that the גמרא
Gemara seems to treat as, sort of as authoritative, but you could
certainly pull out that ברייתא brayta and ask yourself, is there another
approach going on here? And I think the answer would be yes.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now we're going
to... okay, ויקברהו בקברתיו אשר כרה לו בעיר דויד. vayikberuhu bikvurasav asher
karah lo beir David. They buried him in the grave that he
dug for himself in the city of דוד. David. This is חזקיהו...
Chizkiyahu... וישכיבהו במשכב אשר מלא בשמים וזנים. vayashkivuhu bemishkav asher maleh besamim
uzeinim. And they laid him down in his resting place which was
filled... I'm sorry, this is not חזקיהו. Chizkiyahu. This is אסא, Asa,
the king of יהודה Yehuda near the end of the line. Okay,
so they buried him in the grave that he dug for himself
in the city of דוד David and they laid him down in
his resting place which was filled with spices and
זנים. zeinim. מאי בשמים וזנים? mai besamim uzeinim? What does that mean?
רבי אליעזר אומר זיני זיני, Rabbi Eliezer omer zinei zinei, many different
types of spices, all different types of fragrances, all different types of
fragrances. Does זיני zeini mean types? Yes. מיני מיני
בשמים, minei minei besamim, למיניהו לזנוהי. leminehu lezanohei.
רש"י Rashi says the Aramaic word of מין, min, of a species,
its kind, is זנוהי. zanohei. Okay, so
all different types of fragrances. רבי שמואל בר נחמני Rabbi Shmuel bar
Nachmani אומר omer כבשמים שכל המריח בהם בא לידי זימה. kebesamim shekol
hamariach bahem ba lidei zimah. Now there are such sort of, I
don't know, erotic fragrances that anybody who smelled them was sort of,
it whet the,
they would be driven to do an act of improper sex. So
lovely.
So sounds like something you don't ever want to smell. It's like
these ancient customs of burying people with like, you know, food for
the after-
right, oh that's interesting, like מזונות mezonot you mean. No, maybe, that's
an interesting thought. That's an interesting thought. I mean the reason for
fragrances is to counteract the smell of the decaying body. Okay, כי
שוחה ללכדני ki shucha lachadeni because they dug a pit to trap
me. This is ירמיהו. Yirmiyahu. We know he did not have an
easy life. ופחים טמנו לרגלי upachim tamnu leragli and they had traps
were hidden for my legs. Okay, where were we? רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar אומר שחשדו מזונה. omer shechashdu mizona.
So now because, so that they suspected him since we mentioned זנים,
zanim, זנות, zenut, זונה, zona, they suspected him of having sex with
a prostitute. רבי שמואל בר נחמני Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani אומר שחשדו
מאשת איש omer shechashdu meishet ish so that they suspected him of
adultery. So this is, I mean, the reading the שוחה, shucha, presumably
a little play on words שוחה, shucha, חשוד, chashud, okay, so it's
not just a physical trap but they are trapping me in other
ways and getting and discrediting me and so on. בשלמא למאן דאמר
שחשדו מזונה. bishlama lemandemar shechashdu mizona. It works according to the one
that said they suspected him of a prostitute, היינו דכתיב כי שוחה
עמוקה זונה. hainu dechtiv ki shucha amuka zona.
So the word, a prostitute is like a deep pit. It'll pull
you
away, it'll trap you. אלא, ella, so that's the שוחה, shucha, they
dug this pit. אלא למאן דאמר שחשדו מאשת איש, ella lemandemar shechashdu
meishet ish, they suspected him of adultery, מאי שוחה? mai shucha? אטו
אשת איש מינפקא מכלל זונה? atu eishet ish minafka miklal zona?
I don't understand. What's the idea of a pit as a metaphor
for like a prostitute, it's a metaphor for any type of like
forbidden sexual activity and that becomes a pit and a seduction. So
the word שוחה shucha works for that as well, works for the
case of prostitute. תוספות Tosfot by the way says works for the
case of אשת איש. eishet ish. תוספות Tosfot says זונה, zona, if
you look at the little תוספות, Tosfot, שחשדו מזונה דירמיהו כהן הוה
וזונה אסורה בכהן. shechashdu mizona deYirmiyahu Kohen hava vezona asura bekohen. So
it's not just the moral sin of going to a prostitute, it's
specifically he's a כהן Kohen and he's defiling his כהונה. kehunah. But
אשת איש eishet ish is the more severe sin, adultery, and
therefore- well, it's אסור לכהנים assur lekohanim but I
mean it's to marry, right? It's not just, it's not just the-
well, that's an interesting question we debated that, we discussed that at
the end of קידושין Kiddushin whether the איסור issur is just marriage
or even sex. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
okay anyway, so those are the two reads of the way they
dug a pit for ירמיהו. Yirmiyahu. Of course having discussed that one
of the אבות נזיקין avot nezikin is a pit, okay, it seems,
I mean obviously there's the immediate transition was from the word זנים
zanim and זנות zenut and so on, but one wonders if the
גמרא Gemara is also sort of talking about there are other profound
ways in which you can injure somebody, not just by digging pit,
literal literally digging pits.
Against ירמיהו? Yirmiyahu?
Yeah, against ירמיהו. Yirmiyahu. We're now on ירמיהו. Yirmiyahu. Okay, but it
was just the, just because the transition was the word זונה zona
although זונה zona wasn't in the פסוק, pasuk, it was based on
interpretation of the word שוחה, shucha, this pit. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, בשלמא למאן דאמר שחשדו מאשת איש, bishlama
lemandemar shechashdu meishet ish, if they suspected him of adultery, היינו דכתיב
ואתה ה' ידעת את כל עצתם עלי למות. hainu dechtiv ve'ata Hashem
yadata et kol atzatam alai lamut. You God know all of their
plots against me to kill me, okay, because you know this is
a capital crime. אלא למאן דאמר שחשדו מזונה, ella lemandemar shechashdu mizona,
but if they're suspecting him of a prostitute, מאי למות? mai lamut?
So what does it mean they want to kill me? That's not
a capital crime, what they're saying about me. דהשליכוהו לבור הטיט. dehishlichuhu
lebor hatit. No, now that's literal, they threw him into the pit
filled with tar which is in the פסוקים. pesukim. All right, so
there are also physical pits in the world that we do to
people. דרש רבא מאי דכתיב, Darash Rava mai dechtiv, what's meant by
the פסוק, pasuk, ויהיו מוכשלים לפניך, ve'yehyu muchshalim lefanecha, let them be
let them stumble in your presence, בעת אפך עשה
בהם. be'et apecha asei bahem. This is ירמיהו Yirmiyahu again talking. At
the time of your anger you should act God against them. אמר
ירמיהו לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar Yirmiyahu lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu, רבונו
של עולם, Ribbono Shel Olam, Master of the universe, אפילו בשעה שעושים
צדקה, afilu besha'at she'osim tzedakah, even when it's בעת לפניך, be'et lefanecha,
even when they're doing like good things, they're doing צדקה, tzedakah, הכשילם
בבני אדם שאינם
מהוגנים. hachshilem bivnei adam she'einam mehuganim. You should הכשיל hachshil them, you
should cause them to stumble by encountering people that are not of
proper character. That will lead them astray. Oh or excuse me, those
are the people that they'd be giving צדקה tzedakah to. כדי שלא
יקבלו עליהם שכר. kedai shelo yekablu aleihem sachar. In that way they
won't get שכר sachar for giving צדקה tzedakah to these people because
ultimately these people you know are going to use the money for
nefarious purposes and it doesn't really wind up being proper צדקה. tzedakah.
Again, I think that the I would like to
believe- I it's an interesting
question... There are הלכות. halachos. But most of the הלכות halachos about
vetting for צדקה tzedakah are so that you shouldn't feel obligated when
you're not obligated. Right? If you don't want to vet because you
want to trust somebody, and in the end they use the money
improperly, does that mean that you didn't do the מצוה? mitzvah? It's
a good question. Presumably you did the מצוה, mitzvah, you know, I
mean, it's interesting when it gets to a stage where it's obvious
that it was a scam and you should have known, alright, but
anyway, it's an interesting question, like how much is it your responsibility
to vet to, you know, not just to protect yourself, you know,
that you wouldn't and how much have you not done the מצוה?
mitzvah? But anyway, what at least we're saying is that the amount
of שכר sachar you get when the guy winds up using it
for drugs, presumably is less than the שכר sachar you get when
the guy winds up using it for food. But it's a good
it's an interesting halachic question. Anyway, I think also the aggadic role
that this is playing here is that the same way you could
have a pit that's not a physical pit, but by sort of,
you know, allegations against somebody, you could have a stumbling block, a
מכשול, michshol, which is also a type of pit. It's funny that
most of our פרק perek was not about בור, bor, most of
our פרק perek was about שור. shor. בור bor we'll get to
later. But anyway, you could have a type of a מכשול michshol
also. A מכשול michshol is the type of people that you encounter,
right? A מכשול michshol is not just the things you trip over
in the middle of the street. Okay, what did you want to
say Rabbi Dov?
No, it's just there is a concept of לפני הבדאים. lifnei habada'im.
In other words, if it's for the charlatans, you still give צדקה.
tzedakah. In other words, if you'd be vetting every person...
Right, so there are different הלכות halachos about how much you're supposed
to vet. Right. One of the whole ideas about the מתנות עניים
matnos aniyim on פורים Purim is that you're not supposed to vet.
פורים Purim is the day you don't vet people.
Okay yeah, and
you know just running a little bit of the תוספות, Tosafot, so
like when it says just leave their portion you know like of
the תמחוי tamchui or something like that,
yeah yeah, don't give them credit for their מצוה. mitzvah.
Otherwise it sounds like a very you know ungenerous, yeah, but there
is...
what do you want? They're trying to destroy him. Okay, וכבוד עשו
לו במותו. u-kvodo asu lo be-moso. Now this is back to חזקיהו.
Chizkiyahu. They did honor to him in his death. Now we're just
totally digressing to חזקיהו. Chizkiyahu. Okay, because we were talking about חזקיהו's
Chizkiyahu death.
מלמד שהושיבו ישיבה על קברו. milamed she-hoshivu yeshiva al kivro. They had
a ישיבה yeshiva learn by his, by his grave. תוספות Tosafot says
because according to other גמרות Gemaras one of the major accomplishments of
חזקיהו Chizkiyahu was that he spread תורה Torah throughout ישראל, Yisrael, and
a high level of knowledge of תורה. Torah.
And this actually even till today is a practice sometimes that they
have, you know, ישיבות yeshivot learning by a great rabbi's graves. So
פליגי רבי נתן ורבנן, pligi Rabbi Natan ve-rabanan, so the debate how
the duration of time. חד אמר שלשה, chad amar shlosha, three days,
וחד אמר שבעה, ve-chad amar shiva, and some one says seven days
the ישיבה yeshiva was learning.
Temporary ישיבה, yeshiva, yeah, it's hard to get people to spend their
time in a ישיבה yeshiva right in a בית כברות. beis kvaros.
Anyway, ואמרי לה שלשים, ve-amrei leh shloshim, and some say thirty, and
these are different stages of mourning of course. שבעה shiva and שלשים
shloshim are obvious, but if you learn מועד קטן Moed Katan you
see that even three days are the first, are seen as the
prime you know in certain הלכות halachos the primary days within the
שבעה. shiva. Okay, תנו רבנן, tano rabanan, back to doing honor on
his death. וכבוד עשו לו במותו. u-kvodo asu lo be-moso. זה חזקיהו
מלך יהודה שיצאו לפניו שלשים וששה אלף חלוצי כתף. zeh Chizkiyahu melech
Yehuda she-yatzu le-fanav shloshim ve-shisha elef chalutzei katef.
36,000 people in the funeral procession went with their shoulders uncovered. רש"י
Rashi then it means you know that they
did קריעה kriya and on their garment and because of that you
know their shoulder was exposed. תוספות Tosafot says the 36,000 is the
code עשו לו, asu lo, ל"ו. lamed vav. So ל"ו lamed vav
is 36, okay, and then you multiply by a thousand for weight.
דברי רבי יהודה, divrei Rabbi Yehuda, this is what רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says. אמר ליה רבי נחמיה, amar leh Rabbi Nechemiah, ולאו לאחיו
עשו כן? ve-lo l-achiv asu kein? Eh, that's not a big deal.
I mean he was a king! So even for an evil king
they did great honor and you know תוספות Tosafot references you know
another גמרא Gemara that reads the פסוק pasuk of כמספד הדדרימון בן
טברימון ke-misped Hadad-rimmon ben Tabrimmon
which was, where the גמרא Gemara understands it means that that was
like אחאב Achav and a way of indicating that there was a
huge funeral procession for אחאב. Achav. So you know by a king
they all get these huge processions, that's not special about חזקיהו. Chizkiyahu.
So what was special? אלא, ella, or special is when they particularly
mentioned his righteousness, not just honor because of his status as king.
Okay, אלא, ella, here was the honor they did to him. שהניחו
ספר תורה מטתו. she-hinichu sefer Torah mitato. They put a ספר תורה
sefer Torah on his funeral bier, ואמרו, ve-amru, and they said, you
know, in the procession, קיים זה מה שכתוב בזה. kiyem zeh mah
she-kasuv be-zeh. This one fulfilled what was written in that. So he's
like a ספר תורה, sefer Torah, we're burying a ספר תורה, sefer
Torah, he's like an embodiment of the ספר תורה. sefer Torah. That
was the true honor. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says והאידנא נמי
עבדינן הכי? ve-idna nami avdinan hachi? גמרא Gemara says, big deal, so
what?
What's so special? Even today we do it for great rabbis, you
know, you want חזקיהו Chizkiyahu to be greater than just a contemporary
great rabbi.
Yeah, apparently, right. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אפוקי מפיקינן אנוחי
לא מנחינן. apukei mapkinan anuchet lo manchinan.
Maybe nowadays we take out a ספר תורה, sefer Torah, we walk
with a ספר תורה sefer Torah during the funeral procession, but we
don't actually put it on the funeral bier. And ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it
eima, if you want, אנוחי נמי מנחינן, Anuchei nami manchinan, maybe we
also do put it on the bier. It's so funny, like don't
you know what you do? Okay, maybe it means there are rare
times where we'll do that, we'll even put it on the bier,
but קיים לא אמרינן, kei'am lo amrinan, we don't say, we make
it symbolic, but we don't articulate it. When here, by חזקיהו, Chizkiyahu,
they actually articulated it and they said, this fulfilled everything that was
in that. So like a real explicit, this is an embodiment of
a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. Okay. אמר רבה בר בר חנה הוי
אזילנא בהדיה דרבי יוחנן למישאל שמעתא. Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana, havi
azilna bahadei d'Rabbi Yochanan l'mish'alei sh'meita. You know, I was once following
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to ask him certain הלכה halakhic questions, or
כי הוי עייל לבית הכסא, ki havi ayil l'veit hakisei,
and when he would go into the bathroom, some of the גרסא
girsa when he would come out of the bathroom, הוי בעינא מיניה
מילתא. havi ba'ina minei milta. לבית הכסא, L'veit hakisei, right?
What? הוי עייל מ... Havi ayil mi...
No, no, no, כי הוי נפיק מבית הכסא ki havi nafik mi'veit
hakisei is the other גרסא. girsa. Anyway, והוי בעינא מיניה מילתא. v'havi
ba'ina minei milta. Either way, the point is, we were asking him
a question and he couldn't answer because he was just going into
the bathroom, or he had just come out of the bathroom and
we were asking him a question. So before he answered us, after
having gone in and come out, okay, לא פשט לן, lo pashat
lan, he wouldn't give us the answer, עד דמשי ידיה, ad d'mashi
yadei, first he would wash his hands, ומנח תפילין, u'manach tfillin, and
he put on תפילין tfillin because they would wear תפילין tfillin the
whole day. Okay, ומברך, u'mevarech,
and then he'd do the ברכה bracha on תפילין. tfillin. It's interesting,
it says ומברך mevarech after. Okay, so, yeah,
I don't know, it's an interesting question. והדר אמר לן, V'hadar amar
lan, and then he would give us an answer. Okay, now what
does all that have to do with us? So apparently this was
all parenthetical, although in a minute I'll tell you a way that
it wasn't parenthetical at all. But apparently this was all parenthetical, a
very colorful story to get to the fact that here's what רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan told us when we were discussing this issue about
חזקיהו. Chizkiyahu. He told us the following thing. He told us, אפילו
קיים אמרינן. Afilu kei'am amrinan. No, you know what? Nowadays we'd even
be prepared to say, this one fulfilled what was written in that.
So then what was special about חזקיהו? Chizkiyahu? So, לימדי לא אמרינן,
limadei lo amrinan, and we don't say that he taught the people
תורה. Torah. Now of course we didn't say that he said it
about חזקיהו. Chizkiyahu. Now we have to revise that, no, no, that's
what we said about חזקיהו, Chizkiyahu, not that he was an embodiment
of a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, but you know, but actually he
was the spreading of the תורה, Torah, he taught people תורה. Torah.
That's something we did special for חזקיהו. Chizkiyahu. Now the גמרא Gemara
says, this is going to be, I'll read the גמרא Gemara one
way and then I'll tell you a very different way of reading
the גמרא. Gemara. ואמר מר גדול לימוד תורה שהלימוד
מביא לידי מעשה. V'amar mar gadol limud torah she'limud meivi lidei ma'aseh.
Now the גמרא Gemara does not really realize that teaching is not
distinguished from learning. So it's saying teaching is the same as saying
he learned תורה. Torah. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but why,
I'll read רש"י Rashi's way. רש"י Rashi says, why is learning תורה
Torah a higher thing to say than fulfilling תורה? Torah? We taught
at the end of קידושין, Kiddushin, great is learning, that learning brings
to doing. So based on that, what do you think the hierarchy
is? What's the most important thing? Doing. It sounds like doing is
the most important thing. That's the way רש"י Rashi reads it. So,
so why, what do you mean we say nowadays people did, but
we don't say they learned? Doing is better than learning. So why
is it saying it's something greater about חזקיהו Chizkiyahu to say that
he learned? Doing is better! So the גמרא Gemara's answer is, לא
קשיא הא למימר הא למיגמר. lo kashya, ha l'mimar ha l'igmar. No,
no, no, there's a difference between learning and teaching. Okay, so the
hierarchy of importance is, learning is level one, doing is level two,
teaching is level three. That spreads תורה Torah to other people, that
leads to other people doing. So again, that's why that was the
high-. Now the way רש"י, Rashi, yeah, I mean, you know, well
that's actually גמרא Gemara's about that, about sometimes teaching תורה Torah precedes
you actually doing מצוות. mitzvot. Okay, so, so therefore, so according to
רש"י, Rashi, that's the general hierarchy of religious value, of, you know,
learning, doing, teaching. Now of course that raises important questions. Is that
really what we say? Like what is the relationship between learning and
doing? And that was a סוגיא sugya at the end of קידושין.
Kiddushin. What's greater? לימוד Limud is greater or מעשה ma'aseh is greater?
So the answer of the גמרא Gemara there is a very cryptic
answer. The גמרא Gemara says, learning is greater because learning brings to
doing. Okay, which sounds like at least in principle doing is greater,
which is what רש"י Rashi says here. תוספות Tosafot does not like
רש"י Rashi's interpretation because for תוספות Tosafot thinks the point of the
גמרא Gemara in קידושין Kiddushin is that learning is greater. Okay, that
yes, learning maybe has the added benefit of bringing to doing, but
ultimately, if I say, who accomplished more in life? The guy who
did many מצוות mitzvot or the guy who learned a lot of
תורה? Torah? I mean, this is a really powerful question, right? Because
it gets to the question of what do we as a religious
community value? The person who's like, you know, the doctor who's running
around and saving people's lives and doing all those practical מצוות, mitzvot,
or the person who's sitting all his time and learning תורה Torah
and is a big תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. It tends to be
that we value the תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, but maybe we should
be valuing more the doctor who's actually doing מצוות mitzvot and helping
people in a real way, you know? So, so רש"י Rashi says
actually the one who does מצוות mitzvot is of greater value than
the one who learns. Teaching is a different question. תוספות Tosafot says
no, the conclusion of that גמרא Gemara was that learning is better,
maybe because learning also brings about action, but ultimately that's why it
trumps action alone. alone, that's why it trumps action alone, but ultimately
learning is better. So if learning is better, then according to תוספות,
Tosafos, what's the question here? It's better to say that somebody learned
than that somebody did. So תוספות Tosafos says no, the question was
that when you say somebody did, you're already saying that they learned.
Because since we say learning brings about action, you would never praise
somebody's doing if that person had not already learned, because the person
can never fully do a life of doing. It's sort of like,
you know, אין בור, ein bur, you know, אין בור ein bur
what is it, אין בור ein bur something.
חסיד chasid or something like, אין, ein, oh, oh,
oh, אין עם הארץ חסיד. ein am ha'aretz chasid.
אין עם הארץ חסיד.
ein
am ha'aretz chasid.
Right. Yeah, אין בור ירא חטא, ein bur yerei cheit, but I
wanted the אין עם הארץ חסיד. ein am ha'aretz chasid. אין עם
הארץ חסיד. ein am ha'aretz chasid. You know, so תוספות Tosafos says,
so the point isn't that doing is better than learning. The point
is just that doing implies learning. So therefore, what did, why does
it, a better thing to say that he learned? Doing already implies
that, and the answer is no, no, what we added by חזקיה
Chizkiyah was not just that he did and that he learned, but
that he actually taught. Okay, so in the end רש״י Rashi and
תוספות Tosafos basically agree, you know, that that, well, whatever, I mean
in the end they don't agree, I mean they agree to the
conclusion of the גמרא gemara that teaching is on the top, but
it's a really important question of how to read that גמרא gemara
in קידושין. Kiddushin. What is it saying is more important as a
religious achievement? You know, and for רש״י Rashi ultimately it really is
doing. Yes.
What's really interesting and specific in that I think, is the question
of what does it mean to learn something? That is to say
I could learn by watching
somebody act. Right. And watch and learn from their
example and go through my own process of reflection. Right. Or I
could be guided didactically to reflect on the meaning of something.
Right. I mean, it's a good point, like saying that a deep
level, right, that a deep level of doing, right, a lot of
people they grow up in a religious community and they haven't opened
a book, but they just know how do you keep שבת, Shabbos,
how do you put on תפילין, tefillin, how do you דאוון. daven.
Right. And there's something, there's obviously a very powerful, I mean, that's
חיים סולוביצ׳יק's Chaim Soloveitchik's mimetic tradition, some ways in which that's a
deeper learning than learning from the book. But there's also a level
in which there's not a full understanding about, about everything. So you're
right, it's a very excellent point. Now I want to just add
one more fascinating reader of the שאילתות. Sheiltos. The שאילתות Sheiltos says
that this last piece of the גמרא gemara had nothing to do
with חזקיהו. Chizkiyahu. This last piece of the גמרא, gemara, I mean
it, it was a digression, but it wasn't about what they did
for חזקיהו. Chizkiyahu. And what the point was, when רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan came out of the bathroom and he washed his hands and
he put on תפילין tefillin and he made a ברכה bracha and
then he taught, the end of that story, that wasn't a parenthetical
point. The end of that story that says חזקיהו Chizkiyahu didn't say
anything, I mean רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan didn't say anything. רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan didn't tell them oh, כי אמינא
ללימוד לא אמינא. ki amina le'limud lo amina. The whole point of
that story was he first washed his hands and put on his
תפילין tefillin and then he taught us תורה. Torah. And then the
גמרא gemara is saying wait, why did he do it in that
order? If,
if, if לימוד limud is, you know, מביא לידי מעשה, mevi lidei
ma'aseh, then you should be teaching your תורה Torah before you put
on your תפילין tefillin because you should be, now which is a
little funny, like there's a generally in your life לימוד מביא לידי
מעשה, limud mevi lidei ma'aseh, doesn't mean in this one moment I
have to be teaching תורה Torah before I'm putting on my תפילין.
tefillin. But that's anyway the גמרא's gemara's question. Maybe acts are just
symbolic, are, you know, if you have a choice right now, after
you came out of the bathroom, what's the first thing that I
should do? Teach תורה, Torah, put on תפילין? tefillin? Teach תורה, Torah,
תורה Torah is better, you know, and תורה Torah will bring to
action anyway. So the גמרא's gemara's answer is no, no, no, you
know, if it's between learning for yourself and doing, right, then you,
then the, right, wait, how does it go first? Wait, did I
get that right? Remember, hold on, remember, דאמר מר גדול תלמוד שהתלמוד
מביא לידי מעשה, de'amar mar gadol talmud she'hatalmud mevi lidei ma'aseh, so
we should have done לימוד limud first. So לא קשיא. lo kashya.
No, no, so הא למיגמר הא לאגמורי. ha le'migmar ha le'agmorei. First
you do, if it's between learning and doing, wait, I'm trying to
think how this goes. Between learning and doing, you would learn first.
But if it's between teaching and doing, you would teach later. Why?
Because, why? Yeah, so it's not because teaching is less important. I
think it's basically you're just modeling the, you're modeling the hierarchy. Okay,
so that's the same point, like you're modeling the hierarchy. So first
I should learn תורה, Torah, then I should do the action, then
I should teach because that's essentially, that's not the question of importance,
it's not the most important thing you do first. It's actually the
most important thing you do last, what you're, basically the גמרא gemara
is assuming, it's a bizarre idea, that this question of hierarchy should
also translate into me ordering my actions and I should be modeling
the hierarchy. So the first thing I should be doing when I
have an opportunity to do מצוות mitzvos is learn, because learning comes
first. Then I should be doing מצוות, mitzvos, and then I should
be teaching and I should be modeling that hierarchy. So that's how
he reads the גמרא, gemara, a total digression, but fascinating, you know,
application of that idea. Yes, Charlie.
Every ישיבה yeshiva in the world including yours breaks for מנחה. mincha.
Right. Good point. Yes.
No one would say like if I didn't learn something and I
just sat in תהילים Tehillim all day, that that would be better
than, you know, half,
well this גמרא gemara is about רבי Rebbi that would teach all
day and wouldn't say שמע. Shema. I don't want to get into
that, I mean I hear that, okay. Anyway, let's continue. Okay, so
the גמרא gemara says like this. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון
בן יוחי. Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. מאי דכתיב
Mai de'chsiv
What's meant by the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, אשריכם *ashreichem*, praised are you,
זורעי על כל מים *zor'ei al kol mayim*,
you plant your seeds, scatter your seeds on all waters, משלחי רגל
regel השור והחמור *meshalechei regel hashor vehachamor*, sending the leg of the
שור *shor* and the חמור *chamor*. So then we have ושלח את
בעירו *veshilach et be'iro*, משלחי רגל regel, *meshalechei regel*, this is what
the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* of רגל regel, *regel*, getting back to נזיקין
*nezikin*. So the way I think earlier we were dealing a little
sort of you know an אגדתא *Agadeta*, metaphor about what it means
to dig a pit, now we're having a sort of פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* about what it means to do שן shen? *shein* and רגל
regel *regel*, like sending the רגל regel *regel* of the שור *shor*
and the חמור *chamor*. So what does that mean משלחי רגל regel.
השור והחמור *meshalechei regel hashor vehachamor*?
So let's take a look. Hold on a second, somebody just asks
to see if this is urgent.
Hold on one second. I'm sorry. Okay, we're good. Okay. משלחי רגל
regel, השור והחמור *Meshalechei regel hashor vehachamor*. כל העוסק בתורה ובגמילות חסדים
*kol ha'osek baTorah uvigmilus chasadim*, so we were just talking about תורה
*Torah* and about learning, and now we're talking about תורה *Torah* and
doing. Okay. So, but a specific type of doing, a doing of
גמילות חסדים *gmilus chasadim*. So it's sort of similar to that theme
as well. Anybody who involves themselves in תורה *Torah* and גמילות חסדים
*gmilus chasadim*, זוכה לנחלת שני שבטים *zocheh lenachalas shnei shevatim*, merits the
inheritance of two tribes. שנאמר *Shene'emar*, אשריכם זורעי *ashreichem zor'ei*, ואין זריעה
אלא צדקה *ve'ein zeri'ah ela tzedakah*. To plant seeds means to do
צדקה *tzedakah*. שנאמר *Shene'emar*, זרעו לכם לצדקה וקצרו לפי חסד *zir'u lachem
letzedakah vekitzru lefi chesed*. Plant according to righteousness and harvest according to
the kindness. Okay. ואין מים אלא תורה *ve'ein mayim ela Torah*, and
מים *mayim* על כל מים *al kol mayim* means תורה *Torah*. שנאמר
*Shene'emar*, הוי כל צמא לכו למים *hoi kol tzameh lechu lamayim*. So
basically, so if you do acts of righteousness and acts of חסד
*chesed* and you learn תורה *Torah*, okay, and then then זוכה לנחלת
שני שבטים *zocheh lenachalas shnei shevatim*. זוכה לכילה כיוסף *zocheh lechilah keYosef*,
like a bridal canopy like Joseph. שנאמר *Shene'emar*, דכתיב *dechtiv*, בן פורת
יוסף בנות צעדה עלי שור *ben porat Yosef banot tza'adah alei shur*.
So there's the young women went up onto the what do you
call it? On the wall, but also I think it's reading שור
*shur* here as שור *shor* as an ox. Okay. משלחי רגל regel
השור והחמור *Meshalechei regel hashor vehachamor*. What's it do with the bridal
canopy? I don't know, because he's all these young women. So you
know maybe he's getting married to one of them. וזוכה *vezocher*... I
don't know exactly. רש"י rashi *Rashi* just says היינו כילה *hainu kilah*.
Okay. וזוכה לנחלת יששכר *vezocher lenachalas Yissachar*, you get the inheritance of
יששכר *Yissachar*. דכתיב *Dechtiv*, יששכר חמור גרם *Yissachar chamor garem*. So that's
the משלחי רגל regel השור והחמור *meshalechei regel hashor vehachamor* is this
like bony donkey,
meaning like he carries תורה *Torah*. איכא דאמרי *Ika d'amri*, others say
יששכר *Yissachar* is תורה *Torah*.
Well let's see. איכא דאמרי *Ika d'amri*, אויביו נופלים לפניו כיוסף *oyevav
noflim lefanav keYosef*. Others say the enemies fall before you like Joseph.
דכתיב *Dechtiv*, בהם עמים ינגח יחדיו אפסי ארץ *bahem amim yenagach yachdav
afsei aretz*, with those horns. קרני שור הוד לו *karnei shor hadar
lo*? רש"י rashi *Rashi* קרני ראם *karnei re'em*. קרני ראם הוד לו
*karnei re'em hadar lo*. Wait. מה כתוב *mah katuv*? בכור שורו הדר
לו וקרני ראם קרניו בהם עמים ינגח יחדיו אפסי ארץ *bechor shoro
hadar lo vekarnei re'em karnav bahem amim yenagach yachdav afsei aretz*. So
anyway, so it's the שור *shor* there goring these nations. וזוכה לבינה
כיששכר *vezocher levinah keYissachar*, wisdom like Yissachar. דכתיב *Dechtiv*, ומבני יששכר יודעי
בינה לעתים לדעת מה יעשה ישראל *umivnei Yissachar yodei binah le'itim lada'at
mah ya'aseh Yisrael*, what Israel will do. So presumably the wisdom corresponds
to the תורה *Torah* and conquering over the enemies, if you want
to sort of see that as like physical success in this world,
we want to put it a little less violently, corresponding to the
צדקה *tzedakah* and the גמילות חסד *gmilus chesed*. But again, here we
sort of had you know בור *bor* you can sort of lay
traps for people in ways that are not just digging pits. And
this idea of משלחי רגל regel השור והחמור *meshalechei regel hashor vehachamor*
is about like the way you can send out you know your
I would like to read it as you know you can be
negligent and your animals can go out and hurt people, right? And
you can be negligent about your things and your actions and so
on, or you can be intentional about your actions in terms of
תורה *Torah* and גמילות חסדים *gmilus chasadim* and send out ways in
which you are helping and benefiting people, and then you will sort
of reap the you know you'll reap the rewards of that. הדרן
עלך ארבעה אבות *Hadran alach arba'ah avos*. So I don't know if
that was a little stretch, but that's what I'd like to sort
of see, a nice little אגדתא *Agadeta* way of pulling together some
you know meaning of these ארבעה אבות נזיקין *arba'ah avos nezikin*.
Okay. Well I see the ox and the donkey, but it's תורה
*Torah*, but I wonder what the first thing was.
It was נחלת יששכר *nachalas Yissachar*. Yeah, I presume it means the
same. Okay. כיצד keytzad *Keitzad*? Now because the last משנה mishnah. *Mishnah*
or the second to last משנה mishnah *Mishnah* ended with that one
of the things that was מועד muad *mu'ad* was רגל regel. *regel*,
this משנה mishnah *Mishnah* is going to discuss the מועד muad? *mu'ad*
of שן shen *shein* and רגל regel. *regel*. Okay. And the second
פרק perek, *perek*, the first פרק *perek* like I said, בבא קמא
*Bava Kamma* is pretty, pretty darn well organized. So the first פרק
*perek* is like כללים *klalim*, I'd like you to find me another
מסכת *masechet* that opens with such a clear presentation of primary principles.
Okay. And now we go to the more פרטים *pratim* and the
second פרק *perek* is devoted to שן Shein? *shein* and רגל regel,
*regel*. So let's take a look. כיצד הרגל מועדת keitzad ha-regel muedet...
לשבר בדרך הילוכה leshaber bederech hilucha *Keitzad haregel mu'edet leshabber bederech hilucha*?
How is the רגל regel *regel* מועדת mu'edet *mu'edet*? There's two ways
of reading this. In what way is the רגל regel *regel* מועד
muad *mu'ad*? In what way is it you know well not habitual,
is it habitual or in what situations will it pay full? There's
always two ways of reading the word מועד muad *mu'ad*. Does it
mean habitual, does it mean pay full? And the answer to it
is one minute, לשבר בדרך הילוכה leshaber bederech hilucha *leshabber bederech hilucha*,
when the damage it does as it's walking, that's habitual, that's when
it pays full. The other way of reading this is in what
way is the רגל regel, *regel* מועדת *mu'edet*? What way is the
רגל regel מועד muad to damage when it's walking, and then it's
going to sort of spell out the answer at the end of
the משנה. mishnah, Yes.
And then I was looking at this note over here with this
נחל יצחק Nachal Yitzchak or whatever, the one from the first version
they said that they said here, I don't know, but the תרגום
targum translates this as Issachar's wish for property.
Okay. Thank you. Moving on. הבהמה מועדת Ha-behemah muedet so in what
way is it מועד? muad. Or how is it מועד muad in
order to be משבר דרך הילוכה? mishaber derech hilucha? Similarly, הבהמה מועדת
ללכת כדרכה ולשבר, ha-behemah muedet lalechet k'darkah u'l'shaber, an animal is מועד
muad to go normally and to break, so of course it's almost
the exact same words we just said. הרגל מועדת, Ha-regel muedet, הבהמה
מועדת, ha-behemah muedet, משבר בדרך הילוכה, mishaber b'derech hilucha, ללכת כדרכה ולשבר.
lalechet k'darkah u'l'shaber. So like the גמרא's gemara going to say like
what did that second line say that the first line didn't say?
Okay. היתה מבעטת, Hay'tah m'va'etet, here's where it becomes more interesting. היתה
מבעטת או שהיו צרורות מנתזין מתחת רגליה, Hay'tah m'va'etet o she'hayu tzerorot
m'natzin mitachat raglei'ha, if it was kicking, which we know is not
רגל regel? but קרן, keren, or stones were scattering under its legs,
which is half damages but it's a type of a
רגל, regel, so ושיברה את הכלים משלם חצי נזק, v'shibrah et ha-keilim
m'shalem chatzi nezek, half damages. The first way because it's קרן keren
and therefore תם tam ברשות הרבים, b'reshut ha-rabim, the second thing because
it's צרורות, tzerorot, it's indirect, it's כח koach of רגל, regel and
it's ממון mamon and it would pay only though in רשות הניזק.
reshut ha-nizak. So two different types of חצי נזק chatzi nezek that
are being combined here. דרסה על הכלי ושיברתו, Darsah al ha-kli v'shibarto,
it trampled on a vessel and it broke, ונפל הכלי ושיברו v'nafal
ha-kli v'shibaro and that כלי kli that it trampled on broke or
rolled and broke another vessel, okay, so על הראשון משלם נזק שלם,
al ha-rishon m'shalem nezek shalem, the first one is classic רגל regel
pays full, assuming it was in חצר הניזק, chatzer ha-nizak, ועל האחרון
משלם חצי נזק, v'al ha-acharon m'shalem chatzi nezek, the second one was
צרורות. tzerorot. It happened through something that it kicked off, it was
not directly by the body of the animal, and then only pays
half damages.
התרנגולים מועדים Ha-tarnagolim m'uadin that was בהמה. behemah. So התרנגולים, ha-tarnagolim, meaning
and this really, we'll see how the גמרא gemara answers the redundancy
of רגל regel, and בהמה behemah as in it's saying the same
thing, but I think the real פשט pshat literary way of reading
the משנה mishnah is, we have רגל. regel? Let me give you
some examples of a בהמה. behemah. So the first example of a
בהמה behemah are going to be exactly, we're going to describe it
identically. משבר בדרך הילוכה, M'shaber b'derech hilucha, but then I'm going to
give you some subcategories of exceptions of kicking and of צרורות tzerorot
etc. Now let me give you another example of רגל, regel. not
a בהמה, behemah, but a תרנגול. tarnagol. Okay. So what would be
the normal way in which a תרנגול tarnagol would do damage? The
normal way a תרנגול tarnagol does it is it doesn't walk around
and bump into things with its body. I mean maybe it does,
but that's not a normal רגל regel. of a תרנגול. tarnagol. So
the רגל regel. of a בהמה behemah is just what we said,
bumping into things. What's the רגל Regel of a תרנגול? tarnagol? So
התרנגולים מועדים ללכת כדרכן ולשבר. ha-tarnagolim m'uadin lalechet k'darkan u'l'shaber. Oh well.
So what? Oh well, I guess it is the same. Okay. But
but the maybe maybe the exceptions are different. Okay, it is that
is funny actually, it was exact same words. Okay, anyway, היה דלי
קשור ברגליו או שהיו מנתזין משבר הכלים משלם חצי נזק, haya d'li
kashur b'raglav o she'hayu m'adays m'shabert ha-keilim m'shalem chatzi nezek, here are
some examples of exceptions, let's say it had, tell me the word
דלי, d'li, a bucket tied on its leg, or רש"י rashi says
anything tied on its leg is a word of דליל, d'lil, I
don't know what that word would specifically mean, but רש"י Rashi says
it would refer to anything tied on its leg, and it was
you know, and that thing was like or it was you know
and it was bouncing
bouncing around and it broke vessels, so in that type of a
thing that would pay half damages. Again, another example of צרורות. tzerorot.
Okay, so it is pretty funny, you know, I forgot that the
end of the משנה mishnah. ended the exact same way. It is
pretty funny that you have הרגל מועדת ha-regel muedet etc., then you
have a בהמה מועדת behemah muedet and you say exactly what you
said by רגל. Regel התרנגולים מועדין Tarnagolim m'uadin and you say exactly
what you said by רגל. Regel, The only difference between בהמה behemah
and רגל, Regel, even there there wasn't a halachic difference, ah between
בהמה behemah and תרנגולים tarnagolim is the scenarios of צרורות tzerorot are
a little bit different. Okay, let's take a look at the
גמרא. gemara. אמר ליה רבינא לרבא, Amar lei ravina l'rava, so Ravina
said to Rava, היינו רגל היינו בהמה. hainu regel hainu behemah. What
did you add by the second line? First you said רגל Regel.
is מועד to do it when it's walking, then you said בהמה
behemah is מועד. אמר ליה תנא אבות וקתני תולדות. Amar lei tana
avos v'katanei toladot. Oh, it teaches an אב av and a תולדה.
toladah. So what's the תולדה? toladah? So רש"י Rashi says רגל Regel
אב av is רגל ממש, regel mamash, the leg, and the תולדה
toladah is ללכת כדרכה lalechet k'darkah includes not only the leg, but
any part of the animal it bumps into something, its tail wags
something. So one is the רגל, Regel. the literal leg, is מועד
לשבר כדרך הילוכה, l'shaber k'derech hilucha, and then it's any part of
the animal is מועד לשבר כדרך הילוכה. l'shaber k'derech hilucha. Okay. אלא
מעתה, Ela mei-atah, if that's how you're going to read the two
lines, סיפא דקתני, seifa diktani, the סיפא, seifa, which really means the
next משנה, mishnah the משנה mishna we're going to see on י"ט
עמוד ב'. yod tet amud bet. That says השן מועדת. ha-shen muedet.
Now let me just read you the two lines of that משנה.
mishna The משנה mishna there says the following: כיצד השן מועדת לאכול
את הראוי לה, keitzad ha-shen muedet l'echol et ha-ra'ui lah, same type
of a phrase, הבהמה מועדת לאכול פירות וירקות, ha-behemah muedet l'echol peirot
v'yerakot, and then talks about what if it ate כסות וכלים, ksus
v'keilim, what if it ate things that's not ראוי לה. ra'ui lah.
Okay, so whatever, what happened to my eraser?
Again, these are very nicely structured משניות. mishnayot.
Okay, it says כיצד הרגל keytzad ha-regel מועדת...
לשבר בדרך הילוכה and it said הבהמה מועדת להלך
כדרכה ולשבר. ha-behema mu'edet le-halech kedarka u-leshaber. The animal is מועדת to
walk along its way.
Now we're talking about damage that's caused as a byproduct of walking.
לשבר בדרך הילוכה and it said הבהמה, ha-behema, what's the phrase, what
is it, הבהמה מועדת להלך ולשבר. ha-behema mu'edet le-halech u-leshaber. Okay, ולשבר
u-leshaber whatever whatever I know it isn't exactly. So כיצד keitzad? הרגל
and then it says הבהמה ha-behema and then it says תרנגולים. tarnegolim.
Okay, okay? And then it says and here it has an exception.
Okay and then it has צרורות tzrorot as the exception. Okay and
here's צרורות tzrorot as the exception. So it pretty much echoes the
first words and then it gives you the exception, right? The next
משנה mishna. says כיצד השן מועדת לאכול את הראוי לה, keytzad ha-shen
mu'edet leechol et ha-ra'uy lah, את הראוי לה. et ha-ra'uy lah. And
then it has the same thing: הראוי לה הבהמה מועדת לאכול, ha-ra'uy
lah ha-behema mu'edet leechol, לאכול, leechol, what does it say, פירות וירקות,
perot veyerakot, וירקות. veyerakot. So actually here it has a little bit
more of a of a concretization. This remains very abstract so this
gives a little bit more color. But then it has the exceptions
and the exceptions is כסות וכלים. ksut vekelim. Okay I should draw
the exceptions with a different marker. Okay and then it has exceptions.
Okay? So it's the same type of structure. So first it repeats
the rule and then it has exceptions, repeats the whatever, כיצד exception.
Here it added a little bit. It gave you, well, ראוי לה
ra'uy lah means פירות וירקות. perot veyerakot. But one could really say
the whole point of the משנה mishna, was to get to the
exceptions. Okay anyway, but we want to say why did you repeat
this line? And we're saying well it's not just the leg, it's
any part of the animal. So why are you repeating this line?
Okay, this is an אב av and this is a תולדה. tolada.
This isn't
an אב av and
a תולדה. tolada. The only difference here is that you clarified we
meant fruits and vegetables. So it's not the same structure. Okay, so
let's take a look. אלא מעתה ela me'ata סיפא דתני השן מועדת
הבהמה מועדת מאי אב ומאי תולדות? seifa de-tani ha-shen mu'edet ha-behema mu'edet
mai av u-mai toldot? You're not going from the tooth to another
part of the animal. The the השן ha-shen is the tooth and
the second line is the tooth. The second line is just clarifying
fruit and vegetables. So the גמרא gemara said no, אי מהא איכא.
ei me-ha ika. So הוה קא מהדר ליה בבדיחותא. hava ka mahdar
leh bidichuta. So wait, so so רבא Rava responded to רבינא Ravina
and he was like kidding around. ואמר ליה אנא שני חדא. ve-amar
leh ana shani chada. Hey look, I answered one משנה mishna. ואת
שני חדא. ve-at shani chada. You go answer the other משנה. mishna
Okay? So right, exactly. So he says yeah ask me how to
explain the other משנה, mishna, I did my job, you figure out
the other משנה. mishnah. Okay, השתא מיהא hashta mei-ha the גמרא gemara
is saying it's very nice he thought it was a joke but
what's the answer? So אמר רב אשי תנא שן דחיה וקתני שן
דבהמה. amar Rav Ashi tana shen de-chaya u-katani shen de-behema. No, here
the difference is going from רגל Regel. to בהמה. behema. Here the
difference is here it's בהמה, behema, so by implication the first line
is חיה. chaya. And the חידוש chidush is that it's not only
the you know a case of בהמה behema which we'll think is
the classic case, but it applies even to you know untamed animals
as long as you own them, like deer, if you happen to
own deer. סלקא דעתך אמינא ובער ביה בשדה אחר כתיב בהמה אין
חיה לא. salka da'atach amina u-vi'er bi-sdeh acher ktiv behema in chaya
lo. ובער u-vi'er means literally your בהמה behema and not your let's
say you know your undomesticated animal. קא משמע לן דחיה בכלל בהמה.
ka mashma lan de-chaya bichlal behema. No, and if it says בהמה
behema as a general rule that includes חיה chaya as well. וחיה
בכלל בהמה ve-chaya bichlal behema is a I understand. אי הכי איבעי
ליה למתני ברישא. ei hachi ibaye leh le-matni be-reisha. One minute. So
now though what we're saying is אב av and תולדה, אב tolada
av. is the foot, תולדה tolada, is any part of the animal.
So similarly we would say אב av is the בהמה behema because
that's ובער u-vi'er the פסוק pasuk. we get this from, and חיה
chaya is the תולדה. tolada So you reversed the order. It should
have been אב תולדה, av tolada, so here it's תולדה tolada. אב.
av So the גמרא gemara said היי דאתיא מדרשא חביבא ליה. hai
de-atya mi-drasha chaviva leh. Nah, because it would rather start with the
תולדה tolada because that's less explicit in the פסוק, that has to
be derived. רישא נמי ליתני? reisha nami litni? So here too why
not start with the תולדה tolada which was derived from the case
of רגל? Regel. So הכי השתא? hachi hashta? What type of question
is that? התם איידי דאבות נינהו. hatam eidi de-avot ninhu. הכא דאתיא
מדרשא חביבא ליה. hacha de-atya mi-drasha chaviva leh. No no no. Here
חיה chaya and בהמה behema are not אב av and תולדה. tolada.
It's an explicit in the פסוק and inferred but they're both the
אב, av, they're both the animal eating. So if they're both the
אב av we can put the דרשה drasha one first. But when
it's a clear hierarchy of אב av and תולדה tolada we're going
to start with the אב. av. הכא שבקי אב ותני תולדה? hacha
shavki av u-tani tolada? You think we would ignore the אב av
and start with the תולדה? tolada? Okay, that's one answer. אי בעית
אימא איידי דסליק מרגל פתח ברגל. ei ba'it eima eidi de-salik me-regel
patach be-regel. No no no. Here because we really would have put
בהמה behema first, we really would have put the תולדה tolada first,
the דרשה drasha first. But because the previous משנה mishnah, said explicitly
רגל, Regel. we picked up with the phrase רגל here. All right,
none of those answers are super satisfying. But what about the phrase
שן? Shein. Right? No, the previous משנה, mishnah the one I don't
have on the board says you know הרגל מועדת להלך. ha-regel mu'edet
le-halech. So we started with the word רגל and then we did
the בהמה. behema. But really we'd prefer to start with the דרשה.
drasha. First that before we get to the explicit פסוק. It's a
literary, it's a literary. Yeah, but I don't believe any of that
is פשט. pshat. I don't believe any of that is פשט pshat
in the משנה. I do not believe that קצת השן ktzat ha-shen
is חיוב chiyuv in order to tell you בהמה behemah here. Okay,
right. It's just yeah, anyway, it's a little redundancy. I understand. Okay,
let's move on. Let's get to הלכה. halacha. תנו רבנן. tano rabbanan.
Okay. בהמה מועדת להלך כדרכה לשבר. behemah mu’edet l’halech k’darka l’shaber. כיצד?
בהמה שנכנסה לחצר הניזק, behemah she-nichnesa l’chatzer ha-nizak, so once again we're
talking about רגל,
so it has to go into the damagee's domain, the
other person's domain, לחצר הניזק, l’chatzer ha-nizak, והזיקה בגופה, v’hizika b’gufa, and
it damaged with its body, it doesn't have to be with its
leg, דרך הילוכה derech hilucha in its normal way of just moving
around and walking, ובשערה, u’v’sa’arah, it could either mean hair or again
I prefer to read that as its tail, דרך הילוכה derech hilucha
in its normal way of walking, ובאוכף שעליה ובשליף שעליה, u’v’ukav she-aleha
u’v’shlif she-aleha, the I think it's the saddle and the saddlebags, ובפומביא
שבפיה, u’v’pumbiya she-bi-piha, the bit in its mouth. So the point of
all of this is don't think that this is צרורות. tzroros. This
is directly on the בהמה. behemah. It hasn't left the animal's body
and it's being directly manipulated by the בהמה.
behemah. That's not צרורות, tzroros, that's גופו, gufo, okay. ובזוג שבצווארה u’v’zug
she-bi-tzavara or the what do you call
it around the bell around its neck. Okay, now by the way,
that's an interesting question because it's got a bell around the neck
and the bell sort of, you know, maybe swings and that's גופו.
gufo. But we taught in the משנה, it sounded like the chicken
with the דלייא dliya with the rope and the bucket is צרורות.
tzroros. So what is that? Is that because the because it's less
control of how the bucket is moving directly, you know. It's true,
the bucket doesn't move directly based on the movement of the body.
But anyway, it's something we'll get to when we get to the
chicken. Yes? I never remember why I had, I always thought that
just got caught in the legs of a rooster. Like nobody put
something. Yeah, well we'll see that, we'll see those scenarios in the
גמרא. gemara. I'm just raising the issue right now. Okay, וחמור במשאו
v’chamor b’massa’o and a
donkey with its with
its burden that's on it, משלם נזק שלם, meshallem nezek shalem, that
pays full. סומכוס אומר צרורות וחזיר שהיה נובר באשפה, Sumchus omer tzroros
v’chazir she-haya nover b’ashpah, if you have the pebbles case or you've
got a a pig that's rooting around in the dung heap, והתיז
והזיק משלם נזק שלם, v’hitiz v’hizik meshallem nezek shalem, pays full damages.
So the גמרא gemara says הזיק פשיטא, hizik pishita, of course if
it does direct damage it's pays full damages. I mean by the
חזיר chazir case, presumably חזיר, chazir, אלא אימא התיז והזיק משלם נזק
שלם. ela eima hitiz v’hizik meshallem nezek shalem. No, no, no, what
סומכוס Sumchus is saying, by because who would disagree with the case
of the pig? So what סומכוס Sumchus is saying, no, no, the
case of the pig is that it's it's rooting around in the
dung heap and that causes things to splatter and or to scatter
and that causes damage. It's another case of צרורות. tzroros. So סומכוס
Sumchus is basically saying צרורות tzroros pays full damages, okay. What does
a Jew owning a חזיר? chazir? I don't know what to tell
you, okay. צרורות, tzroros, it's a good question. So the גמרא gemara
says okay, צרורות מאן דקא שמעיה, tzroros man d’ka shemayeh, what is
סומכוס Sumchus saying oh צרורות tzroros pays full? Whoever said any any
otherwise? I mean the משנה says otherwise but not in this ברייתא.
braita. So the גמרא gemara says no, חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני, chissorei
mechassra v’hachi katani, you have to read that into the ברייתא. braita.
צרורות כאורחיה, tzroros k’orchaya, if it has a case of צרורות, tzroros,
if it's a normal way like צרורות דרגל, tzroros de-regel, חצי נזק.
chatzi nezek. Okay now, וחזיר שהיה נובר באשפה והתיז והזיק משלם חצי
נזק, v’chazir she-haya nover b’ashpah v’hitiz v’hizik meshallem chatzi nezek, and also
by the case of the pig that would be a case of
צרורות, tzroros, okay, that would be like a צרורות. tzroros. By the
way, that's an interesting question, is it צרורות דשן tzroros de-shen or
is it צרורות דרגל? tzroros de-regel? Right, when the when the pig
is rooting in it, is it rooting to eat? Why why do
pigs root around in the dung heap? Presumably to eat, right, to
find food, no? I don't know. But if it's searching for food,
is that שן Shein or is that רגל? Sounds like it would
be רגל. If the animal is, you know, as it's searching for
food, it's like the animal, if the animal's walking to somewhere to
get the food and it bumped into something that'd be רגל. So
the so the pig is is rooting around in the dung heap
even though it's looking for food, that's רגל. Anyway, one minute, one
minute, one minute. So that's צרורות, tzroros, so that's the תנא קמא
tana kamma that צרורות tzroros pays half, okay. סומכוס אומר לא צרורות
וחזיר שהיה נובר באשפה והתיז והזיק משלם נזק שלם. Sumchus omer lo
tzroros v’chazir she-haya nover b’ashpah v’hitiz v’hizik meshallem nezek shalem. I don't
agree. I think צרורות tzroros pays full damages. Okay, now Michael is
saying one minute, what you've had to say your question. We already
had our whole thing חצי נזק צרורות הלכה למשה מסיני. chatzi nezek
tzroros halacha l’moshe mi-sinai. So we said חצי נזק צרורות chatzi nezek
tzroros was הלכתא גמירי לה. hilcheta gemiri lah. So Michael channeling רמב"ם
Rambam is saying how could anybody disagree? Because רמב"ם Rambam says nobody
disagrees with הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l’moshe mi-sinai. So I will tell
you, Michael, stay tuned בדבר. ba-davar. First of all, הלכתא גמירי לה,
hilcheta gemiri lah, רש"י Rashi says הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l’moshe mi-sinai,
but the נצי"ב Netziv points out that according to, I think he
says some of the גאונים Geonim or whatever, I forget or maybe
even says the רמב"ם, Rambam, I have to check. Anyway, the נצי"ב
Netziv says that הלכתא גמירי לה hilcheta gemiri lah means it's a
law, it's an ancient tradition or an ancient law that's been passed
down and we don't remember exactly the reason behind it, okay, but
it's not a claim that it's a הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l’moshe
mi-sinai. Anyway, here the reason behind it is not far to find,
right, you know, as I said it makes sense. By the way,
it's going to be interesting. Is there צרורות tzroros of שן? Shein
Is there צרורות tzroros of קרן? Keren? But צרורות tzroros of רגל
really does make sense of less liability because it's not just a
technical point, it wasn't the body of the animal. The whole case
of רגל is מתעסק. mis'asek. The whole case of רגל, the act
of the animal that is least defined as an act of נזק
nezek is רגל, because it was not directly intending to do the
act that it, you know, of damaging that thing. Meaning, by eating
it it didn't want to damage, it just wanted to eat, but
it was an intentional act. So you add to מתעסק mis'asek the
idea that it's כוחו, kocho, it's even less connected to the animal.
It's an unintentional act of the animal and it wasn't even the
body of the animal, there's a logic to say that the liability
is less, especially if your concept is not negligence, but if your
concept is my animal did it, I have to pay for it,
how much is this what my animal really did? So that's the
idea of חצי נזק. chatzi nezek. So one answer is that it's
not הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'moshe miSinai. The other answer is although
רמב"ם Rambam would claim and like us to believe that there are
no debates about הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'moshe miSinai, there clearly are
debates about הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe miSinai in the גמרות. Gemaras.
So if this was one of them, it's one of them, but
if this isn't one of them, there are others. Okay, you had
a question? No, I was just I was wondering about the possibility
of having צרורות tzroros as תולדה tolada to שן. Shein. It seems
like every time רש"י Rashi. talks about צרורות, tzroros, it's always תולדה
tolada of רגל. Right, that's in the גמרא. Gemara. But we will
get to other possibilities, meaning what would happen if as an animal
was crunching on some food, the things splattered? Right, I just thought
that רגל by definition is כוחו. kocho. Like שן is by definition
the consumption? Right. So you would so what would you say if
something as it was crunching on food a piece of the food
went and splattered and caused some damage? You would say that's רגל.
Well, the incidental aspect of the act of שן is a רגל.
That means by the fact that it's incidental, you know, it's an
incidental result of an act of שן. Right, so that's interesting. So
we'll see this in the גמרא. Gemara. And how about if you
had צרורות tzroros of קרן? Keren? Would it pay a quarter נזק?
nezek? Right, interesting question. Yes. Isn't it seeking הנאה hana'ah versus just
walking through its normal things? Yes, but the question is what if
in an act of seeking הנאה, hana'ah, in the act of getting
that pleasure, it caused some incidental damage? So is it... קרן? Keren?
Yes, but is it קרן? Keren? There's no הנאה hana'ah from the
incidental damage. So the incidental damage is only an incidental act, so
that might make it a רגל. So that's an interesting question. Anyway
let's move on in the גמרא. Gemara. We will get to these,
now we're raising a lot of questions. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabanan: תרנגולים
שהיו מפריחים ממקום למקום, tarnagolim shehayu mafrichim mimakom lemakom, chickens that were
flying from place to place, ושיברו כלים בכנפיהם, veshibru kelim bechanfeihem, and
their wings broke something, hit something and broke a vessel, משלמים נזק
שלם, meshalmim nezek shalem, that's full, that's רגל. ברוח שבכנפיהם, Beruach shebechanfeihem,
if however they made wind and the wind knocked something over, I
never imagined chickens making so much wind with their wings, but whatever,
משלמים חצי נזק, meshalmim chatzi nezek, since wind, here's a case of
צרורות tzroros without any physical object, just creating wind is a צרורות,
tzroros, it's not your body, it's your כוח, koach, it's your pure
disembodied כוח. koach. Okay, סומכוס אומר נזק שלם, Sumchus omer nezek shalem,
סומכוס Sumchus says full. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we taught another ברייתא,
braisa, תרנגולים שהיו מהדסים על גבי עיסה, tarnagolim shehayu mehadesin al gabei
issa, they were jumping around on the dough, ועל גבי פירות ve'al
gabei peiros or on fruit, וטינפו vetinfu and they soiled it, או
ניקרו o nikru or they pecked at it, and who's going to
eat it after it's been pecked at? משלמים נזק שלם, meshalmim nezek
shalem, you pay full damages. העלו עפר או צרורות, He'elu afar o
tzroros, if they were jumping around and that caused dust or pebbles,
and that got the dough dirty, משלמים חצי נזק, meshalmim chatzi nezek,
half damages. סומכוס אומר נזק שלם, Sumchus omer nezek shalem, full. תניא
אידך, Tanya idach, we taught yet another ברייתא, braisa, תרנגול שהיה מפריח
ממקום למקום, tarnagol shehaya mafrich mimakom lemakom, it was flying around, ויצא
רוח מתחת כנפיו veyatza ruach mitachas knafav and wind came from its
wings, ושיבר את הכלים veshibar es hakelim and broke the vessels, משלם
חצי נזק, meshalem chatzi nezek, half. סתמא כרבנן, Stama kerabanan, סומכוס Sumchus
doesn't argue there, but okay, that's a סתם stam ברייתא braisa going
like the רבנן. Rabanan. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, בשלמא
סומכוס, bishlama Sumchus, now we all know all about צרורות tzroros because
we brought it in in the first פרק, but we imported it
from here. This is the discussion and now we're going to figure
out what is this idea of half נזק? nezek? בשלמא סומכוס קסבר
כוחו כגופו דמי, Bishlama Sumchus kasavar kocho kgufo dami, סומכוס Sumchus I
get, it's your energy, it's your power, it's like your body, so
you pay full. אלא רבנן, Ela rabanan, but the rabbis, please make
up your mind. אי כגופו דמי, Ei kgufo dami, if your כח
koach is like your גוף, guf, and again we normally say כוחו
הוא כגופו, kocho hu kgufo, certainly by a human, but this is
an animal and it's incidental, so there's reasons to say it's not
כגופו, kgufo, but if you were to say it's כגופו, kgufo, כולי
נזק בעי שלומי, kulei nezek bei shalumei, pay full. ואי לאו כגופו
דמי, Vei lav kgufo dami, and if you say it's not like
the animal did it, חצי נזק נמי לא לשלם, chatzi nezek nami
lo leshalem, don't pay anything. הדר אמר רבא, Hadar amar Rava, לעולם
כגופו דמי. le'olam kgufo dami. All right, fine, it is like the
animal did it. וחצי נזק צרורות הלכתא גמירי לה, vchatzi nezek tzroros
hilchata gmiri lah, and it is just a הלכתא גמירי לה, hilchata
gmiri lah, הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe miSinai or an ancient tradition
and we can't really say, you're right, it should be either/or. Of
course, the best explanation is you know it's just like, it's just
like, I mean, whatever, חצי נזק chatzi nezek of קרן. Keren. Are
you negligent or not negligent? You know. We can't absolutely say it
is גופו gufo or absolutely it's not, it's right in the grey
zone, so you pay half. Okay? That's how I would like to
interpret it. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבא: Amar
Rava: כל שבזב טמא, Kol she-bezav tamei, this—look, about this סוגיא, sugya,
it's like when—whenever I read it, I like start to get the
highs because up until now everything is so nice and whatever. Now
all of a sudden you have to import all your knowledge of
הלכות טומאה וטהרה Hilchos Tum'ah v'Taharah and זב, zav,
because רבא Rava uses this as a way
of helping you understand what would be understood as גופו gufo or
as כוחו. kocho. So if you don't really—it's hard for you to
understand the difference between גופו gufo and כוחו, kocho, I'll make it
easy for you. If a זב zav would—if it would be an
analogous case by a זב zav it would be טמא, tamei, that's
גופו. gufo. If by analogous case of
a זב zav it would be טהור, tahor, that's כוחו. kocho. Okay?
Now it should be clear.
All right, so yes, let's get into this great clarification. Yes, the
sugya we just
ended. So—why—how is the גמרא Gemara arguing that it shouldn't be even
חצי נזק? chatzi nezek? In other words, if the animal did
it,
then—then זהו גמורה, zehu g'mura,
but
כוחו—why—I'm kocho missing a piece. If כוחו kocho I thought was like
צרורות, tzoros, right?
No, no, no, but it is—but it is צרורות. tzoros. The question
is, do you define צרורות tzoros as if the animal did it,
or as if it didn't do it? Because if the animal did
it, it should be נזק שלם. nezek shalem. If it's not as
if the animal did it, it's separate and external to the animal,
then it should be nothing. What happened to the entire argument in
the סוגיא sugya that said that it was
indirect? That's the conclusion of the גמרא. Gemara. We only know about
צרורות tzoros because we're talking about it.
In other words, here it was—here actually it was setting it up
as absolute. That's what I said!
Here is where we're finally talking about it. Up until now we've
just been importing the discussion. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara
says: כל שבזב טמא, בנזיקין משלם נזק שלם. כל שבזב טהור, Kol
she-bezav tamei, b'nezikin meshallem nezek shalem. Kol she-bezav tahor, if a זב
zav would touch—would encounter this thing and it would not be considered
touched by a זב, zav, then בנזיקין משלם חצי נזק. b'nezikin meshallem
chatzi nezek. Then it's כוחו kocho and half damages. So the גמרא
Gemara says: רבא, צרורות אתא לאשמעינן? Rava, tzoros ata l'ashmi'inan? What's the
חידוש? chiddush? You're telling us הלכתא צרורות? halachas tzoros? I mean, we
know that. No, well, רבא, עגלה מושכה בקרון קא משמע
לן. Rava, egla moshacha b'karon ka mashma lan. He's talking about what
if you have a wagon that is being—that is
being—like—you know—I mean, excuse me, a calf—wait—עגלה.
עגלה, Egla, egla.
עגלה. egla. I was reading the wagon twice. An עגלה egla was
dragging a קרון. karon. Okay? So what does that mean? So if
a calf is drawing a wagon and the wagon goes over vessels,
is that כוחו kocho or is that גופו? gufo? Okay? So now
how—now by telling you זב, zav, that should explain the answer, right?
So no, I don't know, let's see what רש"י says. עגלה מושכה
בקרון קא משמע לן, Egla moshacha b'karon ka mashma lan, let's look
at רש"י. דבזב טמא אם הלך קרון שהזב עליה אגבי כלים. D'bizav
tamei im halach karon she-hazav aleha agabei kelim.
If a wagon was carrying a זב zav and it went on
top of a vessel, the vessel would be טמא. tamei. Why? He
didn't touch the זב, zav, the זב zav didn't touch it, but
it's the principle of משכב, mishkav, it's like he's resting on the
wagon and the wagon is resting on this vessel, so that's considered
מדרס הזב, midras hazav, you know, מדרס midras is
something he tramples on or he rests on. ובנזיקין נמי, עגלה שמשכה
בקרון אגבי כלים כגופו הוי. Uv'nezikin nami, egla she-mashcha b'karon agabei kelim
k'gufo havei.
It's tightly connected, it's sort of like the שליף שעליה, shlif she-aleha,
the זוג שבצווארו, zug she-b'tzavaro,
it's still sort of connected enough to the body that it's like
גופו. gufo. Okay? ולא כצרורות, אם התיז צרורות מתחת
הקרון. V'lo k'tzoros, im hitiz tzoros mitachas hakaron. Now, if it—it—it some
pebbles scattered and broke vessels, דבזב טהור, d'bizav tahor, so if a
זב zav was on the wagon and pebbles scattered and they hit
a vessel, the vessel would be טהור. tahor. So here too, נמי,
בנזיקין נמי צרורות נינהו. nami, b'nezikin nami tzoros ninhu. It's also צרורות.
tzoros. Okay. תניא כוותיה דרבא. Tanya k'vashei d'Rava.
Back to גמרא. Gemara.
She-טהור, tahor, which means then טהור, tahor, it should be בנזיקין b'nezikin
nothing, but right,
oh no, בנזיקין חצי נזק b'nezikin chatzi nezek as רבא Rava says.
If it's בזב טהור, bizav tahor, it's בנזיקין חצי נזק. b'nezikin chatzi
nezek. Okay. תניא כוותיה דרבא: Tanya k'vashei d'Rava: בהמה מועדת לשבר בדרך
הילוכה, כיצד? בהמה שנכנסה לחצר הניזק והזיקה בגופה דרך הילוכה, או בשערה,
או בזנבה, דרך הילוכה, באוכף שעליה, בשליף שעליה, בפרומיא שבפיה, בזוג שבצווארו,
וחמור במשאו. Behema muedes l'shaber b'derech hilucha, keitzad? Behema she-nichnesa l'chatzer hanizak
v'hizika b'gufa derech hilucha, o b's'ara, o b'zanava, derech hilucha, b'ukaf she-aleha,
b'shlif she-aleha, b'fumiya she-befiha, b'zug she-b'tzavaro, v'chamor b'masso'o. And this ברייתא braita
says, והעגלה מושכה בקרון, v'ha-egla moshacha b'karon, or a calf drawing a
wagon, משלם נזק
שלם, meshallem nezek shalem, you pay full. So that's enough כגופו. k'gufo.
תנו רבנן, Tano rabanan, let's get one more. תרנגולים שהיו מחטטים בחבל
דלי. Tarnegolim she-hayu mechat'tetin b'chevel d'li.
A תרנגול tarnegol was pecking away at the rope of a דלי.
d'li. ונפסק החבל ונשבר דלי, V'nifsak hachevel v'nishbar d'li,
and the rope broke and the bucket broke. משלמים נזק שלם, Meshallmim
nezek shalem, they pay full. Now, and that's a חידוש. chiddush. I
mean, not that the rope, but it's a חידוש chiddush that the
דלי, d'li, because what happened? The דלי d'li fell and broke, so
I would say that's like a type of a כוחו kocho on
the דלי. d'li. But maybe because the דלי d'li and the rope
are seen as one object and it did a direct act to
the דלי d'li rope unit, that's why, like if an animal threw
something—let's say that, right? If an animal bumps into a vessel... Falls
off the wall and it breaks, you don't say, oh well, the
animal didn't break it, its hitting the ground broke it and that's
just כוחו, kocho, right? You don't say that. It bumped into the
vessel, right? So, or bumped into the wall and the vessel was
on the wall, that's enough to גופו gufo and then what happens
afterwards, it's still considered that the גוף guf of the animal encountered
the vessel. So here too the גוף guf of the animal encountered
the bucket rope, and then the bucket broke, that's still גופו. gufo.
Because the rope was tied to the bucket.
Right. Exactly.
That's a different quality than a bucket sitting on the ground.
Exactly. Okay. משלם—no, mishalem but I think in both cases it's נזק
שלם. nezek shalem. Okay, why do you say, right?
Yeah, I see a difference.
All right, but I think they're both נזק שלם. nezek shalem. It
directly encounters the object or the thing connected to the object, and
then what happens afterwards, that's still גופו. gufo. Okay, let's just finish
this.
בעי רבא Ba'ei Rava דאזלא—you d'azla know what, let's just end here
I guess. Okay, so we will pick up tomorrow with find out
Rava's question about a similar type.